{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Eugène Albert’s [yoo-zheen ahl-bair’s] system for this instrument has mostly been replaced\nby one designed by Hyacinth Klosé [HYE-uh-synth CLOSE-uh] and named for flute pioneer\nTheobald Boehm [TAY-oh-bald BAME]. The first of these instruments were produced from a\nchalumeau [shah-loo-moh] with an added register key. Klezmer [KLEZ-murr] music\nprominently features this woodwind instrument, which was was played by such jazz musicians as\nArtie Shaw and Benny Goodman. For 10 points, name this single-reed woodwind instrument\nkeyed in B-flat, which usually has a black body.",
      "answer": [
        "soprano clarinet",
        "clarinet"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During the Congress of Vienna, this composer was commissioned to write three string quartets\nfor its Russian representative, Count Razumovsky [rah-zoo-MAHV-skee]. He included a secondmovement funeral march in his third symphony, which he angrily rededicated to honor \"a great\nman\" after hearing that Napoleon had declared himself emperor. This composer of the Eroica\nSymphony wrote the “Heiligenstadt [HAI-lig-ensh-tot] Testament” about his worsening deafness.\nFor 10 points, name this composer whose ninth symphony includes a setting of \"Ode to Joy.\"",
      "answer": [
        "Ludwig van Beethoven",
        "Beethoven"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler’s absent mother was included in a procession in an 1807 painting of an event\ninvolving him. This man touches a plague victim during a visit to Jaffa in a Jean-Antoine Gros\n[grow] painting, and Charlemagne and Hannibal’s names appear in rock in another painting of\nhim. He crowns his wife in a depiction of his own coronation. In another portrait, he rides a\nrearing horse and points into the air. For 10 points, name this French emperor shown crossing the\nAlps in a painting by Jacques-Louis David [dah-veed].",
      "answer": [
        "Napoleon Bonaparte",
        "Napoleon",
        "Bonaparte",
        "Napoleon I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man composed four anthems, including Zadok the Priest, for various coronations. He included \"La Paix\" [pay] and \"La Rejouissance\" [ray-zhoo-ee-sahnss] in a piece that celebrates the end of the War of the Austrian Succession. Another of his compositions was written for George I, who requested a concert on the River Thames [temz]. Those works by this man are Music for the Royal Fireworks and Water Music. For 10 points, name this German-British composer whose oratorio Messiah includes the \"Hallelujah\" chorus.",
      "answer": "George Frideric Handel"
    },
    {
      "question": "An artist from this country was arrested after depicting this country's revolution in the painting The March of Humanity. Several skeletons in graduation caps appear in \"Gods of the Modern World,\" a work one artist from this country painted at Dartmouth College. A purported depiction of Lenin in a painting by an artist from this country led Nelson Rockefeller to destroy it against its artist's wishes. For 10 points, name this native country of the painter of Man at the Crossroads, Diego Rivera.",
      "answer": "Mexico"
    },
    {
      "question": "The oldest German one of these structures was reconstructed from the original stones in 1961. Many ancient forms of these buildings contain zodiac art, such as the one at Beth Alpha near Gilboa. All of these buildings contain a platform called a bimah or tebah for resting a certain text. Since 1970, many American ones have inserted optional mechitza walls to separate the sexes and all have an ark area that faces Jerusalem. For 10 points, name these buildings used for Jewish religious services.",
      "answer": "synagogues"
    },
    {
      "question": "At a competition in the Soviet Union, American pianist Van Cliburn [CLYE-burn] led an acclaimed performance of this composer's Piano Concerto No. 1 in B-flat minor. This composer supported the eventual victors of the Serbo-Turkish War with his Marche Slave [Marsh slav]. Another of his pieces commemorates the Battle of Borodino by pitting the anthems \"La Marseillaise\" [Mar-SAY-ez] and \"God Save the Tsar\" against each other. For 10 points, name this composer of the 1812 Overture.",
      "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky"
    },
    {
      "question": "This building was constructed with the help of a donation from the governor Zerubbabel. This building, where a table always held a dozen loaves of “showbread,” was the cultural and religious center of the Hasmonean Kingdom, which gained its independence following the Maccabean Revolt. This structure was destroyed on Tisha B’Av in 70 AD, and the Dome of the Rock was built on its former location. The Western, or “Wailing,” Wall is the only remaining portion of, for ten points, what Jewish holy building?",
      "answer": "Second Temple of Jerusalem"
    },
    {
      "question": "A defector from this country conducted the first full recording of Wagner’s Ring Cycle and led the Chicago Symphony from 1969 to 1991. A composer from this nation mocked Shostakovich’s Leningrad Symphony in the “Intermezzo Interrotto” of one work and collected folk songs with his countryman, Zolt´an Kod´aly [koh-dye]. For ten points, George Solti and the composer of a Concerto for Orchestra, B´ela Bart´ok, hail from what nation, the subject of 19 Rhapsodies by Franz Liszt?",
      "answer": "Hungary"
    },
    {
      "question": "Prokhorovka Cathedral commemorates the victory in this battle, which was followed by the Third Battle of Kharkov. The Allied invasion of Sicily led Heinz Guderian to argue that Nazi forces should be held back as a reserve during this battle. This battle, also known as Operation Citadel, saw the introduction of the Panzer tank as a counter to Soviet T-34s. For ten points, name this most destructive aerial battle and largest tank battle in history, fought in 1943 near a namesake Soviet town.",
      "answer": "Battle of Kursk"
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist depicted one of his subjects wearing the Collar of Esses livery chain. A much-copied, though lost, work by this artist depicts his royal patron holding a glove in one hand and reaching for a dagger in the other. He included a polyhedral sundial and a lute with a broken string in a double portrait best known for a memento mori rendered in anamorphic perspective. For ten points, what portraitist of Sir Thomas More and Henry VIII included a distorted skull in The Ambassadors?",
      "answer": "Hans Holbein the Younger"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer depicted the industrialization of the Soviet Union in his ballet The Steel Step and used music from his unperformed ballet Ala i Lolli to write the Scythian Suite. A work by this composer written for an audience of Young Pioneers uses the clarinet to represent a cat, and this composer included the “Dance of the Knights” in a Shakespearean ballet. For ten points, name this Soviet composer of the ballet Romeo and Juliet and Peter and the Wolf.",
      "answer": "Sergei Sergeyevich Prokofiev"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer likely hired horn players from Bohemia for the premiere of a piece whose first suite, in F major, includes an “Adagio e staccato” movement. This composer included “La Paix” [la pay] in a suite for wind band written to celebrate the Treaty of Aix-La-Chapelle, and he included hornpipes in a piece written for a concert for King George I held on a barge on the Thames. For ten points, name this German-born English composer of Music for the Royal Fireworks and Water Music.",
      "answer": "George Friedrich Handel"
    },
    {
      "question": "Edouard de Laboulaye proposed this structure as an international effort. After this structure was completed on Bedloe’s Island, it was celebrated with its city’s first ticker-tape parade. This monument’s base features an Emma Lazarus poem with the verses “give me your tired, your poor, your huddled masses” called “The New Colossus.” For ten points, name this Frederic Bartholdi-designed sculpture that bears a copper torch in New York Harbor.",
      "answer": [
        "Statue of Liberty or Liberty Enlightening the World",
        "La Libert´e E´clairant le Monde"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these ships was deemed too slow for the Pacific Theatre and was used in Operation Leader in Norway. During Operation Torch, one of these ships supported ground troops and was named Ranger. In order to prevent the capture of Port Moresby by Japan, two of these ships were sent to the Coral Sea, leading to the scuttling of one called the Lexington. These ships were not present during the attack on Pearl Harbor. The Yorktown was, for ten points, what type of ship that provides a runway for warplanes?",
      "answer": "aircraft carriers"
    },
    {
      "question": "A statue in this building allegedly features the face of an enemy general carved on the back of its head. This building’s 36 columns are accompanied by 48 stone festoons to indicate the growing number of states. Henry Bacon designed this building in the likeness of a Greek Doric temple, and Daniel Chester French designed a seated marble sculpture inside. Martin Luther King gave his “I Have a Dream” speech on the steps of, for ten points, what building that honors the 16th US President?",
      "answer": "Lincoln Memorial"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer dramatized the destruction of Missolonghi during the Greek War of Indepenedence in his opera The Siege of Corinth. This composer repeated musical phrases in a namesake crescendo; that technique is employed in pieces like the overture to The Thieving Magpie. A galop known as “The March of the Swiss Soldiers” concludes the overture to this man’s final opera, which depicts a Swiss folk hero who shoots an apple off his son’s head. For ten points, name this Italian composer of William Tell.",
      "answer": "Gioachino Rossini"
    },
    {
      "question": "Marie van Goethem worked in this profession and, at age 14, served as a model for a bronze sculpture with a wax-covered skirt. A bronze statuette of a girl wearing bangles was found in Mohenjo-daro in 1926 and is named for this assumed activity. This action is depicted in statutes of Shiva nataraja, in which the god is encircled by a ring of fire with one leg raised. For ten points, name this activity depicted in Edgar Degas paintings of women practicing at the barre or performing in ballets.",
      "answer": [
        "dancing",
        "anything related to dance, including ballet",
        "Little Dancer of Fourteen Years",
        "Dancing Girl",
        "Cosmic Dancer and similar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist painted his friend Adrianus Jacobus Zuyderland dressed in blue with his head in his hands in At Eternity’s Gate, which shares its name with a 2018 film about this man. A landscape painting by this artist depicts a cypress tree and a crescent moon over the town of Saint-Remy. This artist of The Potato Eaters was hospitalized in Arles after injuring himself with a razor in 1888. For ten points, name this Dutch artist of Starry Night and Self Portrait with Bandaged Ear.",
      "answer": "Vincent Willem van Gogh"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man returned to power after the scandal of the Lavon Affair, a botched false-flag bombing operation. Ahdut HaAvoda was founded by this man, who ordered the formation of Unit 101 and organized a massive airlift in Operation Magic Carpet as Prime Minister. During his second term, this man launched an invasion of Egypt, precipitating the Suez Crisis. For ten points, name this first prime minister of Israel.",
      "answer": "David Ben-Gurion"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man recruited Cord Meyer during a mission to manipulate the news media in Operation Mockingbird, and he assigned Sidney Gottlieb to experiment with the possibility of mind control in the MK-ULTRA project. When Mohammed Mossadegh nationalized the oil industry, this man launched Operation Ajax to place Mohammad Shah Pahlavi in power in Iran. This man earned the displeasure of President Kennedy after planning the botched Bay of Pigs invasion. For ten points, name the longest serving head of the CIA, the brother of John Foster.",
      "answer": "Allen Dulles"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sculptures found in temples in Kerala depict lasya, a gentle form of this activity. Ernest Mackay found a depiction of a figure engaged in this activity who wears roughly 30 bangles. A 9th century sculpture found inside a temple in Nallur shows a deity as “Nataraja,” meaning the lord of this activity. At Mohenjo-Daro, a bronze statue of a girl engaging in this activity was discovered in 1926. Sattriya is among the classical forms of this activity in India in which the performer enacts a story. For ten points, name this performing art involving moving to the rhythm of music.",
      "answer": "dancing"
    },
    {
      "question": "A very early example of this art form, Seelewig, was produced in Nuremberg in 1644. The earliest examples of this form include Jacopo Peri’s Dafne and the oldest one still performed, The Coronation of Poppea by Claudio Monteverdi. Rival types of this art form in the 18th century included seria and buffa; examples of the latter include The Barber of Seville. A librettist writes the words for, for ten points, what art form that combines theatrical staging and, usually, classical music?",
      "answer": "opera"
    },
    {
      "question": "This collection was published with an acrostic explanation of its history that spells out the word “ricercar.” This collection’s second piece is a six-voice fugue that was one of the first-ever compositions for piano; that selection from this work answered a challenge made at the Sanssouci Palace in Potsdam by a Prussian king who wrote the original theme. For ten points, name this collection of keyboard music by Johann Sebastian Bach based on a theme given to him by Frederick the Great.",
      "answer": [
        "The Musical Offering or Das Musikalisches Opfer",
        "BWV 1079"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Kazimir Malevich’s 1915 painting of a Black one of these things supported an essay explaining a shift “From Cubism to Suprematism.” Two of these things appear in the background of a Rembrandt self portrait that may be a reference to a legend about Giotto. One of the earliest works of abstraction, Hilma af Klint’s Svanen, is a colorful group of concentric ones of these shapes. Medieval European art frequently depicts God creating the world by using a compass to draw, for ten points, what basic, round shape?",
      "answer": [
        "circle",
        "Black Circle",
        "disk Note: Legendarily, Giotto was asked by Pope Benedict XI to demonstrate his artistic skill, so he drew a perfect circle with a single motion."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this group collaborated on an unfinished opera-ballet about the Polabian Slavs in the 10th century titled Mlada. An 1185 campaign against the Cumans and their Khans is the subject of an opera from this group that features the Polovtsian Dances; another work from this group is about the fall of the Rurikids. The composers of Prince Igor and Boris Godunov, Alexander Borodin and Modest Mussorgsky, were members of, for ten points, what nationalist movement in 19th century Russian music?",
      "answer": [
        "The Mighty Handful",
        "the Mighty Five",
        "Moguchaya kuchka"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A composer from this country who wrote a series of Chˆoros [SHO-roos] and took inspiration from Bach for his Bachianas was commissioned to write his Third Symphony, subtitled “War,” as a celebration of the Treaty of Versailles. A major event in this country calls for afoxˆe music and involves a music competition that takes place at the Sambadrome. Heitor Villa-Lobos is from this country, where Antonio Carlos Jobim and Jo˜ao Gilberto popularized bossa nova. For ten points, name this South American country where samba music is played in the Carnival parades in Rio de Janeiro.",
      "answer": "Federative Republic of Brazil"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this man had his works rejected from the Exposition Universalle, he opened the makeshift “Pavilion of Realism” to display several paintings, including The Artist’s Studio and a massive canvas depicting a funeral in his hometown. During the firebombing of Dresden in World War II, a work by this man depicting two men breaking rocks was destroyed. For ten points, name this French artist of Burial at Ornans and The Stone Breakers.",
      "answer": "Gustave Courbet"
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist reflected his early religious career aspirations in a series of twelve paintings of wheat fields. This artist gave Doctor Felix Rey a portrait which Rey used to repair a chicken coop, but the portrait was later valued at over $50 million. This artist created a series of paintings intended for the Yellow House while in Arles. After an argument with Paul Gauguin [[goh-GAHN]], this artist cut off part of his ear. For ten points, name this Dutch painter, who depicted the view from his asylum room in Saint-Rémy [[sanh REH-mee]] in The Starry Night.",
      "answer": "Vincent van Gogh"
    },
    {
      "question": "This culture built the Nunnery Quadrangle and the Pyramid of the Magician. One of this culture's sites includes the Temple of the Bearded Man, Old Chicken, and the Group of a Thousand Columns. This culture's rain god was Chaac [[chah-AHK]], and this culture used the Puuc [[poo-OOK]] style in its architecture. Another of this culture's sites is located near the village of Pisté [[pee-STEH]] and features sinkholes called cenotes [[seh-NOH-tehs]]. Known for the courts on which its people played the \"ball game,\" for ten points, what is this ancient culture which built Chichen Itza [[CHEE-chen EE-tzah]]?",
      "answer": "Mayans"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer was the grandson of a philosopher who inspired the Haskalah. This composer's Festgesang [[FEST-ge-SAHNG]] was adapted into the Christmas Carol \"Hark! The Herald Angels Sing.\" During a trip to the United Kingdom, this composer's visit to Fingal's Cave inspired his Hebrides [[HEH-brih-dees]] Overture. This composer collected eight volumes of six Lieder [[LEE-deh]] in his Songs Without Words. For ten points, name this Jewish-German composer who wrote the incidental music for A Midsummer Night’s Dream.",
      "answer": "Felix Mendelssohn 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist depicted a protest against the removal of Maria Luisa’s children to France in a painting that shows a group of Turkish soldiers wielding scimitars and daggers attacking a crowd. This artist’s painting The Charge of the Mamelukes is the companion to his painting showing a man in a white shirt and yellow pants holding his hands up in front of a firing squad. For ten points, what Spanish artist depicted Napoleon’s occupation of his homeland in The Third of May 1808?",
      "answer": "Francisco Goya 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 9"
    },
    {
      "question": "When this group began to overrun the FANK, the U.S. initiated Operation Eagle Pull to evacuate personnel. This regime closed most schools as part of its campaign against the \"New People\" and used a former high school building as \"Security Prison 21.\" This party's government killed over a quarter of its country's population at sites known as \"Killing Fields.\" For ten points, name this Communist party led by Pol Pot that controlled Cambodia in the late 1970s.",
      "answer": "Khmer Rouge"
    },
    {
      "question": "Court painter Daniel Maclise depicted this monarch meeting a noblewoman At Hampton Court in one painting. This monarch appears on the bottom left approaching the royal party of Francis I in the landscape painting Field of the Cloth of Gold. This man employed foreigner Hans Holbein the Younger, who depicted this king in a portrait situated next to one of Jane Seymour and this man's father Henry VII [[the Seventh]]. For ten points, name this English king who is depicted in several portraits with his six wives.",
      "answer": "Henry VIII ]"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This movement was satirically criticized in the newspaper Le Charivari [lay sharr-uh-varr-ee]\nby Louis Leroy [loo-ee luh-roy] and took its name from a painting of the harbor of Le Havre [lay\nhahv] over which the sun rises. The Salon of the Refused often exhibited this movement’s works,\nincluding Luncheon on the Grass. For 10 points, name this art movement whose members\nincluded Pierre-Auguste Renoir and Claude Monet.",
        "answer": [
          "Impressionism",
          "Impression"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which American painter's depiction of a girl in a white dress, Symphony in White, No.\n1, was also shown at the Salon des Refusés?",
        "answer": [
          "James Abbott McNeill Whistler",
          "Whistler"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A scalloped dome frames a standing Mary in this artist’s Darmstadt Madonna. Carnations represent the title merchant’s engagement in a portrait of Georg Gisze [gist-zeh] by this man. This court painter of Henry VIII created a work that features a large distorted skull, along with astronomical devices flanked by two men in front of a green curtain. For 10 points, name this Dutch painter of The Ambassadors.",
        "answer": "Hans Holbein the Younger"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Holbein also illustrated this satirical essay, in which the title daughter of Plutus is nursed by Inebriation and Ignorance. Holbein also painted several portraits of its Dutch author.",
        "answer": "In Praise of Folly"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man had the word “Freude” replaced with “Freiheit” while conducting a performance of Beethoven’s Ninth at the Brandenburg Gate in 1989. John F. Kennedy was the dedicatee of his Kaddish symphony. He collaborated with Jerome Robbins and Stephen Sondheim on a musical about warring Puerto Rican and Caucasian gangs based on Romeo and Juliet. For 10 points, name this Jewish composer of West Side Story.",
        "answer": "Leonard Bernstein"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bernstein composed the soundtrack for this Elia Kazan movie about a corrupt longshoremen’s union, in which Marlon Brando’s character laments “I coulda been a contender!”",
        "answer": "On the Waterfront"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A canopy designed by this artist is composed of four Solomonic columns adorned with bees, a symbol of the Barberini family. His two sets of “semicircular colonnades lead up to St. Peter’s Basilica, also featuring his Baldacchino [BAL-duh-“key”-no]. Light shines as an angel pierces the title woman with an arrow in his best known work. For 10 points, name this Baroque [buh- ROAK] sculptor of The Ecstasy of St. Theresa.",
        "answer": "Gian Lorenzo Bernini"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This architect of the San Carlo alle Quattro Fontane worked with Pietro da Cortona and under Bernini on the Palazzo Barberini.",
        "answer": "Francesco Borromini"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer wrote a Mass without woodwinds or low brass “for troubled times,” which gained its nickname from Napoleon’s defeat at the Battle of the Nile. This composer of the Lord Nelson Mass interrupted a quiet second movement with a sudden fortissimo chord in one work, and had performers leave the stage at the end of another work written for his patron, Prince Esterhazy. For ten points, name this “father of the symphony” who wrote the “Surprise” and “Farewell” symphonies.",
        "answer": "Franz Joseph Haydn"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Joseph Haydn’s E-flat concerto for this brass instrument was written for an experimental 5-key model invented by Anton Weidinger.",
        "answer": "trumpet"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man hosted a fundraiser for the Black Panthers that Tom Wolfe described as “radical chic.” His third symphony was dedicated to the memory of JFK and was based on the Jewish prayer for the dead. Another piece by this composer of the Kaddish Symphony included a “rumble” between the Sharks and Jets and songs such as “Gee, Officer Krupke” and “America”. For ten points, what conductor of the New York Philharmonic wrote the music for West Side Story?",
        "answer": "Leonard Bernstein"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Leonard Bernstein also wrote the music for what operetta, based on a Voltaire work that parodied Gottfried Liebniz as Dr. Pangloss?",
        "answer": "Candide"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer’s second symphony was dedicated to George Butterworth, who was later killed in World War I, and includes the Westminster Chimes in its finale. He depicted the doomed expedition of Robert Scott to the South Pole in his seventh symphony. This composer of A London Symphony and Sinfonia antarctica used a violin to depict the title bird in another piece. For ten points, name this British composer of The Lark Ascending and Fantasia on “Greensleeves”.",
        "answer": "Ralph Vaughan Williams"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ralph Vaughan Williams also wrote a Fantasia on a theme of this 16th century Baroque English composer, who composed for Queen Elizabeth I and is best known for a forty-voice motet, Spem in alium.",
        "answer": "Thomas Tallis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this man’s buildings was derided as a crypto-Communist “threat to the New America” by House Beautiful magazine in 1953. That building inspired a similar house by this man’s student, Philip Johnson. This creator of the glass-clad Farnsworth House succeeded Hannes Meyer as the third director of a design school that was closed in 1933 under pressure from the Nazis. For ten points, what modernist architect and final director of the Bauhaus coined the phrase “less is more?”",
        "answer": "Ludwig Mies van der Rohe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ludwig Mies van der Rohe designed an iconic chair for the German Pavilion of the 1929 World’s Fair in this city, also home to Park Guell.",
        "answer": "Barcelona"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One side withdrew from this battle in Operation Ke. This battle was roughly simultaneous with naval engagements at Cape Esperance and Santa Cruz. In this battle, codenamed Operation Watchtower, a midnight raid on Tulagi allowed the securing of a landing area for the Cactus Air Force at Henderson Field. Following this battle, MacArthur was able to begin the process of “island hopping”. For ten points, name this 1942 battle in the Solomon Islands, an Allied victory that allowed U.S. forces to start the Pacific offensive.",
        "answer": "Guadalcanal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Japanese admiral, who ordered the attack on Pearl Harbor, was shot down during a Pacific inspection tour a few months after his defeat at Guadalcanal.",
        "answer": "Isoroku Yamamoto"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer wrote an opera inspired by James Agee and Walker Evans’ Let Us Now Praise Famous Men and wrote a two-movement Clarinet Concerto for Benny Goodman. This composer of The Tender Land depicted the life of an outlaw who was shot by Pat Garrett in another work. This composer also wrote a work for Martha Graham that includes variations on the Shaker hymn “Simple Gifts.” For ten points, name this American composer of the ballets Billy The Kid and Appalachian Spring.",
        "answer": "Aaron Copland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A speech by Vice President Henry Wallace inspired this short Copland work for brass and percussion. This fanfare was commissioned by Eugene Goossens of the Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra in 1942.",
        "answer": "Fanfare For The Common Man ”fanfare” not needed after mentioned"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two answers required. During an election contested between these two men, the endorsement of John Crittenden swung the election to the winner. A speech by one of these men was used to begin the other’s Cooper Union speech, given to elaborate his views by invoking the Founding Fathers. One of these men issued the Freeport Doctrine, articulating his support for popular sovereignty, during a series of senatorial debates between these two men in 1858. For ten points, name these two Illinois politicians, who finished first and fourth in the Presidential election of 1860.",
        "answer": "Abraham Lincoln and Stephen Douglas BONUS:Duringthedebates,Douglaswasheavilyquestionedabouthissupportforthispieceoflegislation, which repealed the Missouri Compromise. ANSWER: Kansas-Nebraska Act 3 Sculptures of caryatids were used in place of these structures in the Erechtheion on the Athenian acropolis. A temple at Karnak includes enormous examples of these structures decorated with hieroglyphs in its hypostyle courtyard. Their capitals can be decorated with various objects, including acanthus leaves on the top of the Corinthian type. For ten points, name these architectural elements that often bear the weight of a roof. ANSWER: columns"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Corinthian columns are the most ornate of the three ancient order; this simplest of the three was characterized by plain capitals, funnel-like shapes, and no bases.",
        "answer": "Doric order"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer included movements titled “The Absence” and “The Return” in a piano sonata inspired by his patron Archduke Rudolph fleeing Vienna, Les Adieux. He wrote a set of 33 variations on a waltz he supposedly dismissed as a “cobbler’s patch.” This composer of the Diabelli Variations also wrote a sonata “quasi una fantasia” that reminded Ludwig Rellstab of an object shining over Lake Lucerne. For ten points, name this German composer of Fu¨r Elise and the Moonlight Sonata.",
        "answer": "Ludwig van Beethoven"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Archduke Rudolph had to flee Vienna due to the actions of what man who was initially planned to be the dedicatee of Beethoven’s Symphony no. 3, Eroica?",
        "answer": [
          "Napoleon Bonaparte",
          "either",
          "both names",
          "Napoleon I"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One composer from this present-day country used an extinct liturgical language for his Glagolitic Mass. Another composer from this country included a furiant in a suite inspired by Johannes Brahms’ Hungarian Dances and wrote his final symphony, partially inspired by Longfellow’s Song of Hiawatha, while he visited the USA. A symphonic poem about this country’s Vysehrad [vish-eh-rahd] castle premiered after its composer lost his hearing; that work opens a set of six pieces titled Ma Vlast. For ten points, name this modern-day country, the home of Leos Janacek [yahn-ah-check] and the composer of the Slavonic Dances and the New World Symphony, Antonin Dvorak [d’vor-zhak].",
        "answer": [
          "Czechia",
          "Czech Republic"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to composers like Janacek and Dvorak, Czechia’s musical history includes this composer of the aforementioned Ma Vlast and The Bartered Bride.",
        "answer": "Bedrich Smetana"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer quoted the “Habanera” from Bizet’s [bee-zay’s] Carmen in the opening movement of a symphony whose finale was described as a “parody of shrillness” in the spurious autobiography Testimony. An opera by this composer focusing on Katerina Izmailova prompted Joseph Stalin to denounce him as “formalist” in the article “Muddle Instead of Music.” For ten points, what persecuted composer of Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District dubbed his Fifth Symphony “A Soviet Artist’s Reply to Just Criticism” and wrote fifteen symphonies in total?",
        "answer": "Dmitri Shostakovich"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "“Muddle Instead of Music,” as well as an additional article denouncing Shostakovich entitled “Ballet Falsehood,” was published in what official Soviet newspaper?",
        "answer": "Pravda"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This building’s shadow can be used to tell time, thanks to a nearby park designed in the shape of sundial. Three gold coins with rectangular holes are the logo of this building, which was designed to appear as multiple money boxes stacked atop each other in the feng shui style by architect C.Y. Lee. This was the world’s tallest building until 2010, when it was surpassed by the Burj Khalifa. For ten points, name this Taiwanese skyscraper.",
        "answer": "Taipei 101"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Malaysian skyscraper was surpassed by Taipei 101 as the world’s tallest building in 2004, though it still holds the record as the tallest twin towers complex.",
        "answer": "Petronas Twin Towers"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this conflict, Henri Huet [en-ree oo-ay] photographed a silhouetted corpse falling out of a helicopter. A sculpture commemorating this war by Frederick Hart shows three soldiers of different ethnicities in U.S. Army and Marine Corps uniforms. That sculpture stands near another commemoration of this war, built after its designer won a contest; that memorial is engraved with over 50,000 names. For ten points, name this war for which Maya Lin built a Veterans Memorial wall.",
        "answer": "Vietnam War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A photo of Mary Ann Vecchio weeping over a body was taken at an anti-Vietnam War protest at this Ohio university.",
        "answer": "Kent State University"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This artist included a depiction of Sappho holding a scroll with her name on it, as well as Dante, Boccacio, and the nine muses in a depiction of Mount Parnassus. This artist, who began his career under Perugino, included a self-portrait as the Greek painter Apelles in one of his four frescoes for the Stanza della Segnatura, commissioned by Pope Julius II. For ten points, name this Italian painter who painted Plato and Aristotle conversing in his The School of Athens.",
        "answer": [
          "Raphael",
          "either",
          "both underlined parts of Raffaello Sanzio da Urbino"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Raphael’s School of Athens also includes a portrait of this architect, the planner of St. Peter’s Basilica, using a compass.",
        "answer": "Donato Bramante"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This initiative may have led to the murder of exiled president Jango Goulart. As part of this initiative, Celestina Almada was forced to listen to her husband Martin’s torture over telephone, prompting a search for documentation of this initiative in the Archives of Terror. Manuel Contreras was one of the early masterminds of this initiative, which was originally run by the DINA secret police but soon expanded to include Jorge Videla’s Dirty War in Argentina. For ten points, name this 1970s-era operation in which South American governments silently eliminated communist dissidents.",
        "answer": "Operation Condor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One leader who participated in Operation Condor was this Paraguayan dictator of German heritage. During his 35 year rule, he renamed Ciudad del Este in honor of himself.",
        "answer": "Alfredo Stroessner"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this composer’s most famous pieces names an operation during the Blitz that destroyed much of Coventry. This composer commemorated a British triumph at the Battle of Vitoria in his piece “Wellington’s Victory.” Another of this composer’s works was dedicated “to the memory of a great man” after its original dedicatee, Napoleon, invaded Austria. That symphony was his Eroica. For ten points, name this German composer of nine symphonies, the last of which contains the “Ode to Joy”.",
        "answer": "Ludwig van Beethoven"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Beethoven piano sonata, which was compared to the image of Lake Lucerne at night, was dedicated to a woman who may have been Beethoven’s “Immortal Beloved,” the addressee of an unsent love letter. ANSWER:MoonlightSonata(orPianoSonataNo.14inC-sharpminor;prompton“Quasiunafantasia”) (4) This man rediscovered a river formerly known as the Mauritius; at that river, his crewmate John Colman was killed via an arrow to the neck. This captain of the Half Moon met his end shortly after breaking camp at James Bay when his crew mutinied and set him adrift during his search for the Northwest Passage. For ten points, name this English explorer for the Netherlands who now names a large Canadian bay.",
        "answer": [
          "Henry Hudson BONUS: The Hudson’s Bay Company began in 1670 and primarily dealt in this industry, which employed coureur de bois in New France. ANSWER: fur trading",
          "equivalents, like pelt trading",
          "furs of specific animals, like beavers",
          "foxes"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Frank Lloyd Wright influenced one of the earliest buildings made with this material, Robert van’t Hoff’s Villa Henny in Utrecht. This material was used in the construction of 146 nearly-identical apartments that were built for the 1967 World’s Fair; that prefabricated housing complex designed by Moshe Safdie, Habitat 67, is a famous example of Brutalist architecture. Romans constructed the Pantheon’s dome with the “unreinforced” type of, for ten points, what building material that binds gravel or stones with cement?",
        "answer": "reinforced concrete"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Concrete was also heavily used by this architect, who was commissioned by Jawaharlal Nehru to redesign Chandigarh, India. The Villa Savoye embodies this man’s “five points” of architecture.",
        "answer": "Le Corbusier"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A travelogue named for the scent of females from this place was written by a man whose ceramic of a female savage inspired a figure in Pablo Picasso’s Young Ladies of Avignon. A work depicting people from this place should be viewed from right to left and was finished after its painter attempted suicide by overdosing on arsenic. In that piece about this place, each of the major groups acts alongside a blue Buddha-like idol that is meant to represent “the Beyond.” The work Where Do We Come From? What Are We? Where Are We Going? was set on, for ten points, what French Polynesian island that was frequented by Paul Gauguin?",
        "answer": "Tahiti"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Due to its shared setting and subjects, Gauguin’s painting The Spirit of the Dead Watching was compared to this painting, which caused an uproar at the 1865 Paris Salon. Despite her oppositional gaze, the maid is ignored by the title figure of this work.",
        "answer": "Olympia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this state, Rafael Moneo designed a major postmodern cathedral to avoid right angles. Philip Johnson designed this state’s huge all-glass Crystal Cathedral. This state was the center of Jim Jones’s religious movement before the foundation of Jonestown in Guyana. Aimee Semple McPherson founded the Foursquare Church in, for ten points, what US state where Spanish catholics established missions in cities like San Francisco and Los Angeles?",
        "answer": "California"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This charismatic Christian movement originated with the Azusa Street Revival in California.",
        "answer": [
          "Pentecostalism",
          "word forms"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer depicted the 1994 Los Angeles earthquake in I Was Looking at the Ceiling and Then I Saw the Sky. An opera by this composer begins with the “Chorus of Exiled Palestinians” and the “Chorus of Exiled Jews” and centers on the hijacking of the cruise ship Achille Lauro. The ballet “The Red Detachment of Women” is featured in an opera by this composer that begins with the title character stepping of The Spirit of ‘76. For ten points, name this American minimalist composer of Nixon in China.",
        "answer": "John Coolidge Adams"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This 69-year-old Jewish-American man was murdered on the Achille Lauro in 1985 and is the subject of Adams’ aforementioned opera.",
        "answer": [
          "Leon Klinghoffer",
          "The Death of Klinghoffer"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event led to the resettlement of 18,000 children in the Cuban resort town of Tarara. The Liquidators group was formed to bulldoze pine trees after this event, which required the building of a concrete sarcophagus. A high incidence of thyroid cancer was discovered among people in the vicinity of this event, which created the Red Forest. Pripyat was evacuated as a result of a failure in reactor 4 during, for ten points, what 1986 nuclear disaster in Soviet Ukraine?",
        "answer": "Chernobyl nuclear meltdown or disaster, etc."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mikhail Gorbachev advocated for this policy of “openness” in the wake of Chernobyl and other incidents of Soviet non-transparency.",
        "answer": "glasnost"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician hid his prostate cancer from the public and died in 1996 a few days after enjoying roast ortolan at his final meal. This leader controversially authorized Operation Satan, the bombing of the Rainbow Warrior ship off of New Zealand’s coast. This man was forced into a system of cohabitation with E´douard Balladur and Jacques Chirac, the latter of whom succeeded him in 1995. For ten points, name this first socialist president of France.",
        "answer": "Francois Mitterand"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Rainbow Warrior was operated by this organization at the time of its sinking in 1985.",
        "answer": "Greenpeace"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An artist from this country created a hyper-realistic sculpture of a pope being struck by a meteorite titled The Ninth Hour. Another artist from this country painted v-shaped rays of light emanating from a street light; that artist helped lead a movement whose manifesto declares that “a racing car is more beautiful than the Victory of Samothrace.” For ten points, name this home country of the 20th century art movement Futurism, which was led by Giacomo Balla and Filippo Marinetti.",
        "answer": "Italy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Maurizio Cattelan’s The Ninth Hour depicts this pope sprawled on the floor under a massive rock. This man was severely wounded in 1981 in St. Peter’s Square by gunman Mehmet Ali Agca [AHD-cha].",
        "answer": "John Paul II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These pieces most likely formed from clausula sections of plainchant melodies called organum, exemplified by the Notre Dame school. An isorhythmic piece in this genre titled “Nuper rosarum flores” was written for the consecration of the Florence Cathedral. Thomas Tallis’ Spem in alium and Mozart’s “Ave verum corpus” are examples of, for ten points, what polyphonic settings of sacred Latin texts, a genre of Renaissance music often contrasted with contemporary secular motets?",
        "answer": "motets"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This 15th century composer honored Brunelleschi’s work on the Florence Cathedral with “Nuper rosarum flores.” This French composer of the Burgundian school was one of the last to use isorhythm.",
        "answer": "Guillaume Dufay"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Condor Legion, a detachment of this organization, was sent to aid Nationalist forces in the Spanish Civil War. Under Albert Kesselring, this organization conducted Operation Retribution, which resulted in the death of over 17 thousand Yugoslav civilians. On Adlertag, or Eagle Day, this organization lost nearly fifty aircraft while attempting to gain superiority over the British Royal Air Force. For ten points, name this military organization, the aerial warfare branch of the Nazi Wehrmacht.",
        "answer": "Luftwaffe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1937, the Luftwaffe contributed to the destruction of this city in Spain, memorialized in a painting by Pablo Picasso.",
        "answer": "Guernica"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Robert E. Simon owned this location that was built for the Oratorio Society. Zankel Hall is connected to this building, which was designed by William Burnet Tuthill and contains the Stern Auditorium and Ronald O. Perelman Stage. Arturo Toscanini often used this building to record the NBC Symphony Orchestra for RCA Victor. Jascha Heifetz [[YAH- shah HAI-fetz]] jokingly replied that the way to get to this venue was \"to practice.\" For ten points, name this prestigious performing arts venue in New York City, named for a Scottish philanthropist.",
        "answer": "Carnegie Hall"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "On the opening night of Carnegie Hall, May 5, 1891, a concert was conducted by Walter Damrosch [[DAHM-roash]] and this Russian composer of the Pathétique Symphony.",
        "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The name of this movement may have been coined by critic Clarence Cook. This movement's founder was depicted in the painting Kindred Spirits by Asher Brown Durand. A visit to Northampton, Massachusetts inspired a work by one artist from this movement titled The Oxbow. This movement's founder drew from ancient Roman sculpture for paintings like Destruction in his Course of Empire series. For ten points, name this American art \"school\" founded by Thomas Cole and named for a body of water in eastern New York.",
        "answer": "Hudson River School"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other Hudson River School artist studied under Thomas Cole, and his paintings Niagara and The Heart of the Andes both drew thousands of viewers to single-work exhibitions in the 1850s.",
        "answer": "Frederic Edwin Church"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this artist's works was commissioned to honor soldiers who were killed fighting the Central Powers at Târgu Jiu [[tehr-goo-ZHEE-ooh]]. That work, his Sculptural Ensemble, includes his The Gate of the Kiss and Endless Column. This artist carved a marble sculpture of a head titled Sleeping Muse, and the Salon des Indépendants removed this artist's sculpture Princess X for its allegedly phallic appearance. For ten points, name this groundbreaking Romanian sculptor, a pioneer of modernism.",
        "answer": "Constantin Brâncuși ]"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the best-known Brâncuși sculptures was the subject of a legal battle after U.S. customs classified it as \"manufactured metal\" instead of an artwork.",
        "answer": [
          "Bird in Space",
          "Pasărea în văzduh",
          "L'Oiseau dans l'espace"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In commemoration of a victory in the Franco-Prussian War, this composer wrote the Triumphlied [[tree-OOMF-LEED]] and dedicated it to the reigning Kaiser Wilhelm I. This composer's awarding of an honorary degree from the University of Breslau led to his rearrangement of student drinking songs in the composition Academic Festival Overture. The birth of Bertha Faber's second son inspired this composer to write his \"Wiegenlied\" [[VEE- gehn-LEED]], commonly nicknamed his \"Lullaby.\" For ten points, name this Romantic-era German composer of the Tragic Overture.",
        "answer": "Johannes Brahms"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brahms wrote the opening notes of which Austrian Waltz King's composition, \"The Beautiful Blue Danube\"?",
        "answer": [
          "Johann Strauss II",
          "Johann Strauss the Younger",
          "or Johann Strauss the Son",
          "or Johann Strauss Jr."
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Late 18th-century pianos often had a pedal named for either this place or a group from this place which simulated the sound of a bell or a bass drum. The makam system was used for music theory in this state, where genres included the fasil and pesrev. The tanbur lute and ney flute were often used in this state, where cymbal-heavy marching music was sometimes played by elite soldiers recruited from the Balkans. For ten points, Janissary bands originated in what empire, where music could be performed for the sultan in Constantinople?",
        "answer": [
          "Ottoman Empire",
          "Turkey",
          "or Turkish Empire",
          "Ottoman music",
          "or Turkish music"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What composer's eleventh piano sonata contains a final movement usually known as the \"Rondo Alla Turca\" for its Ottoman-inspired sound?",
        "answer": [
          "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart",
          "Johannes Chrysostomus Wolfgangus Theophilus Mozart"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event led to the ten percent decrease in NASCAR race lengths and the cancellation of the 24 hours of Daytona in support of the government. Secretary of State Henry Kissinger's negotiating of the Israeli forces away from the Sinai peninsula led to the end of this crisis. The phrase \"Don't be Fuelish\" was used during this event, which was prompted by the Yom Kippur War. An embargo by the Organization of Arab Petroleum Exporting Countries during the Nixon and Ford administration led to, for ten points, which \"crisis\" of the late 20th century?",
        "answer": [
          "1973 Oil Crisis",
          "descriptions of the the US not having Oil in the 1970s",
          "OPEAC oil embargo of the 1970s"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The oil embargo was a direct response to which specific operation during the Yom Kippur War, in which the U.S. airlifted over twenty-thousand tons of military supplies to Israel?",
        "answer": "Operation Nickel Grass"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The European Theater of World War II",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country invaded on September 1, 1939, marking the beginning of World War II.",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that faced the Blitz and employed the Royal Air Force.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "French line of fortifications that did not account for a blitzkrieg through the Ardennes.",
          "answer": "Maginot line"
        },
        {
          "question": "Desperate, late German offensive, also known as Operation Watch on the Rhine, that made a namesake shape in Allied lines.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Bulge"
        },
        {
          "question": "1940 evacuation of Allied troops by everything from naval vessels to fishing boats.",
          "answer": [
            "Dunkirk evacuation",
            "Operation Dynamo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed operation to “end the war by Christmas” that wanted to capture Nijmegan [ny-may-hen] Bridge.",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Market Garden",
            "either",
            "both parts"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Operation, part of Bodyguard, that tricked the Germans into defending Norway and Pas de Calais, rather than Normandy.",
          "answer": "Operation Fortitude North and/or South"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of lower Normandy, where fierce fighting took place in Operations Charnwood and Perch.",
          "answer": "Caen"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding Ivan the Terrible, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding ivan the terrible, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire he led from Moscow",
          "answer": [
            "Russian Empire",
            "Imperial Russia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cathedral he had built commemorating the seizure of Kazan and whose architect he legendarily had blinded",
          "answer": [
            "Saint Basil's Cathedral",
            "Cathedral of Vasily the Blessed",
            "Cathedral of the Intercession of the Most Holy Theotokos on the Moat",
            "Pokrovsky Cathedral"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret police he created to serve as his bodyguards",
          "answer": [
            "Oprichniki",
            "Oprichnina"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Major city in which that secret police force committed a massacre in 1570",
          "answer": "Novgorod"
        },
        {
          "question": "Period started after the death of his son which ended with the rise of the Romanovs",
          "answer": [
            "Time of Troubles",
            "Smuta"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ineffectual son who succeeded him, the last Rurikid tsar",
          "answer": [
            "Fyodor I Ivanovich",
            "Feodor the Bellringer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former member of Ivan's personal guard who became the first non-Rurikid tsar of his country",
          "answer": "Boris Fyodorovich Godunov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crimean Khan who was aided in burning Moscow by boyars who were terrified of Ivan's madness",
          "answer": [
            "Devlet I Giray",
            "Giray 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8 Post-Colonial Philippines"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Watergate",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Watergate scandal, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President whose administration was affected by Watergate, leading his resignation.",
          "answer": "Richard Milhouse Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of establishment which was broken into during Watergate.",
          "answer": [
            "Hotel or Watergate Hotel",
            "Office Building"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Governing body of the opposition party of the Republicans whose headquarters was robbed.",
          "answer": "Democratic National Committee or DNC"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Committee\" which organized the Watergate break-in.",
          "answer": [
            "Committee to Re-Elect the President",
            "CREEP",
            "or CRP"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "press conference.",
          "answer": "\"I am not a Crook\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Pair of Washington Post reporters who broke the Watergate scandal after communicating with \"Deep Throat.\"",
          "answer": "Bob Woodward and Carl Bernstein or Robert Upshur Woodward and Carl Bernstein"
        },
        {
          "question": "Informal name for the resignations by two attorney generals after they were ordered to fire Archibald Cox.",
          "answer": "\"Saturday Night Massacre\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Chief operative of the \"White House Plumbers\" who faced jailtime for his involvement.",
          "answer": "George Gordon Liddy"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A depiction of this place in the parekklesion [pare-uh-KLEE-see-onn] of the Chora\n[CHOH-ruh] Church features Jesus holding the hands of Adam and Eve. This place is\ncommonly depicted as a \"mouth\" in manuscript paintings, which often feature depictions\nof its (20 pts) ",
        "“harrowing.” The New Testament repeatedly refers to its inhabitants “weeping\nand gnashing” their (10 pts) ",
        "teeth. This place is depicted in the right-hand panel of Bosch’s Garden\nof Earthly Delights and is usually on the right in paintings of the Last Judgement. For 10 points,\nname this place often described as a location of eternal torment."
      ],
      "answer": "Hell"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man received a warning from the Boston police for including a dominant seventh in an arrangement of “The Star-Spangled Banner”. W.H. Auden wrote a four-haiku text for this man’s composition Elegy for (20 pts)",
        "J.F.K., and he collaborated again with Auden on the William Hogarth-inspired opera The Rake’s Progress. One of his most famous works opens with a high (10 pts)",
        "bassoon solo and was accompanied by Sergei Diaghilev’s [dee-AH-gi-levs] choreography for Vaslav Nijinsky [nih-JIN-ski]. For 10 points, name this composer who was present during the riot sparked by the 1913 premiere of his ballet The Rite of Spring."
      ],
      "answer": "Igor Stravinsky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one of this artist’s paintings, the title officer is supported by several soldiers under a waving Union Jack during Battle of Jersey. George Augustus Eliott points toward several sinking Spanish soldiers in The Siege of (20 pts)",
        "Gibraltar, a work by this artist of The Death of Major Peirson. Another of his painting shows a silver kettle in the hands of the (10 pts)",
        "silversmith Paul Revere. In his most famous painting, El Morro castle looms behind a harpooner saving a man from an anatomically incorrect marine creature. For 10 points, name this painter of Watson and the Shark."
      ],
      "answer": "John Singleton Copley"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During his years in England, this man published A Treatise on the Improvement of Canal Navigation. His contemporary rivals included Oliver Evans, whose designs were deployed in Western (20 pts)",
        "waters. A protege of Benjamin West, this painter-turned-engineer designed a proto-submarine called the Nautilus that brought him to the attention of his partner (10 pts)",
        "Robert Livingston. He used a design from Boulton and Watt to propel his launch of the Clermont on the Hudson River. For 10 points, identify this American founder of the first successful steamboat venture."
      ],
      "answer": "Robert Fulton"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Nearly 2,500 of these things were built in Carl Strandlund’s factory in Columbus, Ohio, which was funded by the Reconstruction Finance Corporation; those things, named “Lustron,” were made using enameled-steel that didn’t require (20 pts)",
        "painting. Levitt & Sons built over 17,000 of these things on Long Island, then discriminated against African- Americans by only selling or (10 pts)",
        "renting them to white families. For ten points, name these buildings, whose supply drastically increased after World War II to meet the demand of returning GIs and the Baby Boom."
      ],
      "answer": "houses"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Giulio Clovio landed this artist a job in Rome in the Palazzo Farnese, but he was later dismissed for being against the teachings of Michelangelo. His works were judged to not completely follow the rules of the Counter-Reformation, preventing him from working for (20 pts)",
        "Philip II. One of his works contrasts a dark and stormy sky with green hills and a cathedral spire, and in another, the (10 pts)",
        "clouds part to receive Don Gonzalo Ruiz. For ten points, name this Mannerist artist of Burial of the Count of Orgaz and View of Toledo, a Spanish artist from Crete."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "El Greco",
        "Dom´enikos Theotok´opoulos"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist used his son, Jarvis, as a model for Michael Schwerner in one work. Another work by this artist shows four U.S. Marshalls escorting six-year-old Ruby Bridges to an all-white school. This man’s work for LOOK magazine include Southern Justice and The (20 pts)",
        "Problem We All Live With, and he depicted a man dissenting at a town meeting and an old woman serving a turkey as part of a series inspired by (10 pts)",
        "FDR’s 1941 State of the Union. For ten points, name this artist who illustrated the Four Freedoms series and many covers for the Saturday Evening Post."
      ],
      "answer": "Norman Rockwell"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer reused a march from his unfinished opera Undine for the Allegretto of his second symphony, which quoted three Ukrainian folk songs. He wrote a piece to benefit wounded soldiers in the Turko-Serbian war. Nikolai Rubenstein rejected his first piano concerto, which (20 pts)",
        "Van Cliburn performed in Moscow in 1958 to win his namesake piano competition. This composer of the Marche Slave and Little Russian Symphony wrote another work featuring (10 pts)",
        "“La Marseillaise,” “God Save The Tsar,” and some cannon fire. For ten points, name this Russian composer of the 1812 Overture."
      ],
      "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An abandoned opera by this composer depicted the secret Vehmic courts of medieval Germany, and he wrote another opera based on the memoirs of Florentine sculputor Benvenuto Cellini. This composer of Les francs-juges dedicated a work to veterans of the July (20 pts)",
        "Revolution; four offstage brass bands are called for in that Requiem. He also wrote a five-movement work that includes a “scene in the fields” and combines the Dies Irae [dee-ACE ee-RAY] with its (10 pts)",
        "id´ee fixe [ee-DAY feex] in the final movement, a dream of a witches’ Sabbath. For ten points, what composer’s unrequited love for the singer Harriet Smithson inspired his Symphony Fantastique?"
      ],
      "answer": "Hector Berlioz"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This subject of one of this artist’s paintings wears a medallion given to him by Alexander the Great while resting his hand on a bust of an ancient poet. This artist’s numerous self-portraits include one etching with his wife, (20 pts)",
        "Saskia. He included a young girl in a yellow dress with a chicken hanging from her belt in his portrait of arquebusiers under the command of (10 pts)",
        "Frans Banning Cocq. For ten points, name this Dutch artist of The Anatomy Lesson of Dr. Nicolaes Tulp and The Night Watch."
      ],
      "answer": "Rembrandt van Rijn"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist designed stained glass in memory of Dag Hammerskj¨old for the United Nations Headquarters dedicated to Peace. He used a Cubist style to show a (20 pts)",
        "purple-coated violinist standing on top of two houses, based off his childhood in a Hasidic community. At the top of one painting, he included a woman playing the violin upside-down and a (10 pts)",
        "green-skinned man holding a glowing tree while facing a farm animal. For ten points, name this Russian painter of I and the Village."
      ],
      "answer": "Marc Chagall"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Police banned this composer’s work after a demonstration followed a performance of his one-act opera Kaschchey the Deathless. The censors banned this man’s 1907 opera The Golden (20 pts)",
        "Cockerel for its implied criticism of Tsar Nicholas II. A suite by this man opens with the movement “The Sea and Sinbad’s Ship,” and his opera The Tale of Tsar Saltan includes an virtuosic excerpt that accompanies Prince Guidon’s transformation into an (10 pts)",
        "insect. For ten points, name this Russian composer of Scheherazade and “Flight of the Bumblebee.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of this artist’s works was inspired by the Zong massacre. This artist requested that he be buried in the canvas of his work showing the title character across from the tomb of Sychaeus [sih-KAY-us]. This “painter of light” and artist of (20 pts)",
        "Dido Building Carthage obscured Hannibal’s army in one of two works titled Snow-Storm. In the 1840s, he painted the (10 pts)",
        "Maidenhead Railway Bridge with a train barreling toward the viewer. For ten points, name this painter of Slave Ship and Rain, Steam, and Speed."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph Mallord William Turner"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One artist from this movement painted the f-holes of a violin on a classical Ingres [AHNG] nude and experimented with photograms now named after him. The New York (20 pts)",
        "Armory show emboldened another artist in this movement to exhibit everyday objects, such as snow shovels and bottle racks, as (10 pts)",
        "“readymades;” that artist from this movement also signed “R. Mutt” on a urinal. Man Ray and Marcel Duchamp belonged to, for ten points, what avant-garde art movement that flourished after World War I?"
      ],
      "answer": "Dadaism"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Thomas Aquinas’s “Pange lingua” forms the basis of one of these pieces by Josquin des Prez [joh-skan dez prezz]. One of these compositions includes material originally written for the death of Augustus II and accession of Augustus III of Poland, and unusually calls one movement (20 pts)",
        "“Symbolum Nicenum.” Another of these works supposedly convinced the Council of Trent to not ban polyphony and was written for Pope (10 pts)",
        "Marcellus by Giovanni Palestrina. J.S. Bach wrote a B minor example of, for ten points, what type of sacred musical work that includes Credo and Kyrie movements and sets the weekly Catholic liturgy?"
      ],
      "answer": "masses"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country arrested hundreds of “Swing Kids,” who preferred English language music. The opera Jonny Strikes Up by Ernst Krenek was criticized in a music exhibition in this country, which commissioned (20 pts)",
        "Carl Orff to write incidental music for Shakespeare’s Midsummer Night’s Dream to replace Felix (10 pts)",
        "Mendelssohn’s work. Jazz and twelve-tone music were banned as “degenerate music” by, for ten points, what country from which Arnold Schoenberg and other Jewish composers fled in the 1930s?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nazi Germany",
        "the Third Reich"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer called for a piano with lutheal attachment in his violin rhapsody Tzigane. In 1910, this man orchestrated a piece meant to evoke a dancing infanta in Baroque-era Spain. A pair of brothers killed by the same shell in (20 pts)",
        "World War I were eulogized in a “Riguadon” this composer included as part of his Tombeau de Couperin. This composer of Pavane for a Dead Princess also wrote a (10 pts)",
        "repetitive piece for Ida Rubenstein consisting of one long crescendo. For ten points, name this French composer of Bolero."
      ],
      "answer": "Maurice Ravel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This piece was commissioned for the price of 100 ducats, half paid in advance. Composition of this piece was delayed by time spent finishing La Clemenza di Tito and Die Zauberfloete. The figured bass line was all that was (20 pts)",
        "finished for some later movements of this piece, most of which was completed by Franz Sussmayr. Constanze, the wife of this work’s composer, tried to keep its unfinished nature a secret after the (10 pts)",
        "death of its composer in 1791. For ten points, name this musical piece that Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart believed he was composing for his own funeral."
      ],
      "answer": "Mozart’s Requiem mass in D minor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist, who appealed to Republican sentiments with his painting Lictors Bring to Brutus the Bodies of His Sons, produced a propaganda piece in which stones are inscribed with the words (20 pts)",
        "“Carolus Magnus” and “Hannibal.” This man depicted a revolutionary clutching a pen in his bathtub after he was stabbed by Charlotte Corday, then depicted his later patron (10 pts)",
        "crossing the Alps at the Saint Bernard Pass. For ten points, name this French artist who painted The Coronation of Napoleon and Josephine and The Death of Marat."
      ],
      "answer": "Jacques-Louis David"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a film from this country, the title character is created by a clerk’s typo; that film’s score was composed by the composer of the Scythian Suite. Another composer from this country dedicated a string quartet, which opens with a (20 pts)",
        "DSCH motif, “to the victims of fascism and war;” that composer from this country also featured an “invasion” theme and a theme from his opera (10 pts)",
        "Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District in his Leningrad Symphony. For ten points, name this home country of Sergei Prokofiev and Dmitri Shostakovich."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Soviet Union or USSR",
        "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
        "CCCP",
        "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer requested no applause at the premiere of one of his works, which opens with a movement juxtaposing the Kyrie [keer-ee-ay] with the tenor solo “What passing bells for those who (20 pts)",
        "die as cattle?” Wilfred Owen poetry is used in that work, which this man helped conduct at its premiere at the re-consecration of (10 pts)",
        "Coventry Cathedral. Another work by this composer displays the various sections of an orchestra for children. For ten points, name this British composer of War Requiem and The Young Person’s Guide to the Orchestra."
      ],
      "answer": "Benjamin Britten"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s wife suffered a miscarriage after she heard the radio report of this man’s death, helping lead to the journalistic practice of informing families before reporting the names of fatalities. This man died after chartering a (20 pts)",
        "flight from Mason City, Iowa to Moorhead, Minnesota whose other passengers included “The Big Bopper” and (10 pts)",
        "Ritchie Valens. This artist, famous for his horn-rimmed glasses, recorded with The Crickets. For ten points, name this singer of “That’ll Be The Day,” an early rock-and-roll star who was killed in a 1959 plane crash that became known as “The Day the Music Died.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Buddy Holly or Charles Hardin Holley"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group was criticized for employing the Gehlen Organization in launching Operation Bohemia, where a Czech detonator was successfully secured. This group’s leader, William Colby, helped compile a set of documents known as the “Family Jewels” that detailed their (20 pts)",
        "assassination efforts. Carlos Armas was supported by this group during Operation PBSUCCESS, in which the United Fruit Company convinced this group to (10 pts)",
        "launch a coup d’etat in Guatemala. Allen Dulles once led, for ten points, what American foreign intelligence service?"
      ],
      "answer": "Central Intelligence Agency or CIA"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer’s patriotic works include Carillon, a recitation for speaker and orchestra in honor of Belgium during World War I. An oratorio by this man was composed for the Birmingham Music Festival and is based on a Cardinal (20 pts)",
        "Newman poem. Jacqueline du Pre made her 1962 concert debut performing this composer’s Cello Concerto in E minor. A march by this composer of The (10 pts)",
        "Dream of Gerontius served as the recessional for the marriage of Prince Charles and Princess Diana. For ten points, name this English composer of the Pomp and Circumstance marches."
      ],
      "answer": "Sir Edward William Elgar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist created an oil painting in which a bicyclist frightens horses drawing a carriage as they maneuver out of the way. This artist of The Right of the Road depicted the opening of the Wounded Knee massacre in an illustration for (20 pts)",
        "Harper’s Weekly. This artist, who sometimes collaborated with his friend, author Owen Wister, created a bronze sculpture depicting a man (10 pts)",
        "struggling to keep hold of the mane of a horse. For ten points, name this artist known for his scenes of the Old American West, such as The Bronco Buster."
      ],
      "answer": "Frederic Remington"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer included characters like Human Frailty in his Homer-inspired opera The Return of Ulysses to his Homeland. This composer used an excerpt from Jerusalem Delivered for an opera that contains one of the (20 pts)",
        "earliest uses of tremolo. Ottavia sings “Addio, Roma” in an opera by this composer about the crowning of Nero’s mistress, The Coronation of Poppea. (10 pts)",
        "Eurydice fails to return to the mortal world in the most famous work by, for ten points, what Italian composer of L’Orfeo, one of the earliest surviving operas?"
      ],
      "answer": "Claudio Giovanni Antonio Monteverdi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist painted a full-length portrait of Muhammad Dervish Khan, an ambassador sent by Tipu Sultan to France. This artist indicated the recent death of a child named Sophie with an empty bassinet draped with a black cloth held back by (20 pts)",
        "Dauphin Louis Joseph. In that painting, this artist’s patron wears a red dress in an attempt to repair the (10 pts)",
        "reputation that had been damaged by a painting of this artist’s patron wearing a blue-feathered straw hat and a striped gold sash over a scandalously informal white gown. For ten points, name this court painter for Marie Antoinette."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "E´lisabeth Louise Vige´e Le Brun",
        "Madame Le Brun"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Isamu Nogachi's sculpture Floor Frame is displayed in this building's garden, making him the first artist of Asian lineage to be exhibited here. Childe Hassam's painting The Avenue in the Rain is displayed in this building. James McNeill Whistler and Thomas Jeckyll collaborated on the (20 pts)",
        "Peacock Room in this building. An enslaved person rescued the Lansdowne portrait from this building during the (10 pts)",
        "War of 1812. For ten points, name this building in Washington, D.C., whose decoration has historically been overseen by the First Lady."
      ],
      "answer": "White House"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This composer was the alleged author of the posthumously published memoir Testimony. This composer's ballet The Limpid Stream was denounced by Platon Kerzhentsev [[plah-TOHN kehr-ZHEN-tsef]] for its depiction of peasant farmers. This composer was attacked for (*) formalism in the Pravda article \"Muddle Instead of Music.\" This composer's seventh symphony debuted during a Nazi (*) siege of its namesake city. For ten points, name this frequent target of Joseph Stalin, the Soviet composer of the Leningrad Symphony."
      ],
      "answer": "Dmitri Shostakovich 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An artist created a painting during this war depicting a politician bleeding out while being protected by freedman Peter Salem. Artist John Trumbull served in this war, later painting a scene of William Phillips and another general surrendering during this war. (20 pts)",
        "Emanuel Leutze [[LOIT-zuh]] painted multiple scenes of this war, including one where several figures including James (10 pts)",
        "Monroe and Nathaniel Greene traverse a half-frozen river. For ten points, name this war, the setting of Washington Crossing the Delaware."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Revolutionary War",
        "American Revolution"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Portraits of this artist often feature a broken nose, reflecting an incident in which Pietro Torrigiano [[tohr-EE-jee-AH-noh]] punched him in the face. During Pentecost in 1972, a disturbed geologist named Laszlo Toth vandalized this artist's (*) Pietà. One of this artist's paintings was the subject of the \"fig leaf\" campaign. Due to a mistranslation of the word for \"halo,\" this artist created a sculpture of (*) Moses with two horns. For ten points, name this Italian renaissance artist, who painted The Last Judgement and the Sistine Chapel ceiling."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Michelangelo Buonarroti",
        "Buonarroti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) On a Richard Denton-hosted Channel Four docuseries, examples of these devices were constructed and tested including a giant crossbow and an early parachute. An unbuilt one of these devices intended for military use was fitted with a ring of light cannons underneath a (20 pts)",
        "turtle-like shell. Several of these devices intended for flight were unsuccessfully launched from hills outside of (10 pts)",
        "Florence. The aerial screw is one of the most notable examples of, for ten points, what collection of machines sketched in the codex's of the artist of the Mona Lisa?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Leonardo Da Vinci's inventions",
        "any answer indicating machines, vehicles, flying devices, etc. designed by Leonardo Da Vinci",
        "either Leonardo",
        "Da Vinci in any answer"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A fantasia for piano titled Agonia e morte di [this man] was written by Franz Xaver Süssmayr [[SOOS-my-er]] who was also recruited to finish another work by this man in 1791. Georg Fredrich Daumer claimed that this composer was murdered by freemasons for revealing their secrets in an opera in which the (20 pts)",
        "Queen of the Night enlists Tamino to save her daughter. This composer's life was depicted in a namesake film directed by (10 pts)",
        "Miloš [[MEE-loash]] Forman. For ten points, name this Austrian composer of The Magic Flute."
      ],
      "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1937, this organization became the namesake of an orchestra conducted by Arturo Toscanini that transformed into the Symphony of the Air in 1954. This organization hired Peter Adler to conduct a namesake Opera Theatre that premiered Amahl and (20 pts)",
        "the Night Visitors in 1951. Doc Severinsen, Max Weinberg, and Kevin Eubanks have led in-house bands on this company's late-night (10 pts)",
        "shows. For ten points, name this radio and TV network which trademarked the three-chime sequence that plays over its peacock logo."
      ],
      "answer": "NBC or National Broadcasting Company"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A tableau by this artist depicts the historical Battle of Taillebourg [[TIE-bur]] during the Saintonge [[sahn-TAHNG]] War. While an attaché to a diplomatic envoy to the Kingdom of (20 pts)",
        "Morocco, this artist painted the Orientalist work Women of Algiers. The toppling of Charles X [[the Tenth]] is represented by this artist in a painting depicting a bare-breasted women carrying the tricolour [[tree-koh-LOHR]] flag of France. Liberty (10 pts)",
        "Leading the People was painted by, for ten points, which French Romantic artist?"
      ],
      "answer": "Eugène Delacroix or Ferdinand Victor Eugène Delacroix"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Composer Aaron Copland [[KOHP-land]] set a speech at one of these events in Alton to music, and the recently invented Pitman Shorthand allowed writers to keep up with the orators at these events. The ability of territories to exclude (20 pts)",
        "slavery through local legislation was espoused during these debates in the Freeport Doctrine. A Democrat and a future (10 pts)",
        "Republican president vied for a Senate seat in Illinois during, for ten points, which 1858 debates?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Lincoln-Douglas Debates Great Debates of 1858 before \"1858\" is read",
        "prompt on partial answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The predecessor to this weapon was intended to be used in the never-realized Operation Downfall. Operation Pacer IVY removed this weapon from one country and stored it on (20 pts)",
        "Johnston Atoll, after which it was destroyed in Operation Pacer HO. The tactical use of this weapon was tested during the Malayan Emergency, after which Secretary of State Dean Rusk suggested it could be used lawfully during another conflict. This carcinogenic (10 pts)",
        "chemical weapon was used to destroy high density foliage used by Viet Cong guerillas. For ten points, name this herbicide mixture heavily deployed by the United States during the Vietnam War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Agent Orange or Herbicide Orange",
        "Rainbow Herbicide",
        "Agents White, Blue, Purple, Pink,",
        "Green before \"Pacer\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An act of arson on this building by a slave inspired the term \"Herostratic Fame,\" in which one does a misdeed for \"fame [sought] at any cost.\" Though it was funded by a Lydian king, the poet Callimachus [[cah-leh-MAH-kus]] attributed this building to the (20 pts)",
        "Amazons. Alexander the Great offered to rebuild this wonder in the 4th century B.C. before being met with the response, \"it would be improper for one god to build a (10 pts)",
        "temple to another\" by the citizens of an Ionian city. One of the Seven Ancient Wonders, for ten points, what was this holy site in Ephesus?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Temple of Artemis or the Artemision",
        "Temple of Diana"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A month after this work’s premiere, it was re-scored for a performance at Foundling Hospital. Due to the Duke of Montagu’s insistence on the omission of non- martial instruments, this piece's composer was forced to remove the intended (20 pts)",
        "string parts. Thomas Desaguliers [[duh-sah-gool-YEH]], who was elected to the Royal Society for his artillery research, was fire master at this work's premiere. The signing of a treaty in Aachen is commemorated in this piece, which was commissioned to celebrate the end of the War of the (10 pts)",
        "Austrian Succession. For ten points, name this monarch-approved suite by George Frideric Handel."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Music for the Royal Fireworks",
        "Royal Fireworks Music"
      ]
    }
  ]
}